Animation Number 1
I have finally decided to recall the events of that Golden Week, that time when I fooled around with Hanekawa Tsubasa to my heart's content.
It's a bitter memory, an astringent memory, and yet a memory that is somewhat sweet and sour, but it is
a memory that I want to forget if possible, and even if that were not possible, I want to act as if those events never happened. Those nine golden days are the days I shall recall.
To put this in a chronological context, it was approximately one month after the two weeks of spring
break between my second and third years of high school, the time that I spent in hell.
That was when—
She was drawn in by a cat.
A cat.
A mammal of the family Felidae in the order Carnivora.
And so, ever since Golden Week,
I have been unable to stand cats.
I'm afraid of cats.
Yes. Just like how I'm afraid of Hanekawa Tsubasa.
Now, I'd like you to hear about the dream I had last night.
Animation Number 1
（暦(こよみ)）う〜ん
（月火(つきひ)）何 二度寝してんだ
Die.
（月火）死ね
（暦）うっ
Araragi
Wh-What the hell, Tsukihi?!
月火 お前 何すんだ！
Are you trying to murder your own brother?!
兄を殺す気か！
A brother who sleeps in all the time can go to hell.
二度寝するようなお兄ちゃんは
死んでいいに決まってるじゃない
Karen-chan and I
せっかく私と火憐(かれん)ちゃんが
起こしてあげたのに
even went out of our way to wake you, too.
寝るとか 意味分かんない
You should just die.
死ねばいいんだ 死ねばいいんだ
Just die.
Just die!
死ねばいいんだ！
We're just getting started
（暦）
お前 冒頭からキャラ設定
めちゃくちゃになってんぞ！
and you're already out of character!
People say they can't really tell
私はどうも ほかのみんなに比べて
what kind of character I am compared to everyone else.
キャラが立っていない
ということだから
試みにヤンデレになってみたんだよ
So I thought I'd try being a yandere.
Yandere? More like a psychopath!
（暦）
ヤンデレっつうか それ狂人だよ！
あ〜 それにしても
今日からゴールデンウィークか
So Golden Week starts today, huh?
It's been pretty lame so far.
いいことなんか １個もねえなあ
（月火）
初日から いきなり後ろ向きだね
お兄ちゃん
That's rather pessimistic for the first day, Onii-chan.
まだゴールデンウィークは始まって
９時間もたってないよ
It's been less than 9 hours since Golden Week started.
Oh, right.
そうだ　恋について語ろうぜ
月火ちゃん
Let's talk about love, Tsukihi-chan.
Love?
恋？
episode forbidden
tsubasa family
Font Face Used  HG PMincho B
Sit
Animation Number 34
So, what kind of love are we talking about, Onii-chan?
（月火）
で どんな恋の話をするの？
お兄ちゃん
You're only in middle school,
（暦）中学生なりに彼氏がいる—
but you have a boyfriend and have undoubtedly
discussed the subject a hundred times with your friends.
おそらくは仲間内から数々の
恋愛相談を受けているであろう—
百戦錬磨のお前にしか
これは 聞けないことなんだが
You're the only one I can ask.
The truth is, I'm interested in a girl in my class.
実は今 クラスに
気になる子がいるんだ
I think I might have feelings for a girl who ended up in my class after the reshuffle.
クラス替えで
一緒の組になった女子に
ひょっとすると僕は 好意を
抱いているかもしれないんだ
What?!
なんとまあ！
Is it that shocking?
そんなに驚くことかよ
Of course it is!
そりゃ驚くよ
It's beyond shocking! It's a bombshell!
驚くっていうか とどろくよ！
"Your human intensity falls when you make friends."
〝友達を作ると
人間強度が下がるから〞
That's the stuff you usually spout, but you actually fell for someone!
とか イタいことを公言していた
お兄ちゃんに
好きな相手が できただなんて
This is shocking enough to make dogs talk!
これは犬が
しゃべったくらいの衝撃だよ！
Don't get ahead of yourself.
（暦）早とちりをするな
I'm just interested in her at this point.
気になるってだけで
また ひょっとして
かもしれないってだけで
This is just a vague possibility that I'm not sure of yet.
まだ確定したわけじゃないんだ
Oh?
（月火）ぬぬ？
（暦）だから
That's why I'm begrudgingly asking you for advice.
お前に したくもない相談を
しているんだよ
How do you figure out whether or not you're in love with a particular member of the opposite sex?
とある異性がいたとして
自分がそいつのことを
好きかどうかって
どうやって決めればいいんだ？
Animation Number 51
Um... I'm sorry, Onii-chan.
（月火）
えっと ごめん お兄ちゃん
Come again?
何だっけ もう一度 言ってくれる？
Could you repeat that?
What? You weren't listening?
何だよ 聞き逃しちゃったのか？
Listen properly.
今度はちゃんと聞けよ
How do you figure out if you love someone of the opposite sex?
異性を異性として好きかどうかって
どうやって決めればいいんだ？
In other words, how far can your feelings for someone go and still stay neutral,
つまり 相手に対して抱く感情は
どの時点までが普通で
hate
neutral
love
どの時点からが好意になるんだ？
and at what point does it become love?
う〜ん ツッコミっていうのは
The role of the straight man is traditionally yours, so it's a bit awkward for me to be doing it...
基本的に
お兄ちゃんがやることであって
私のやることじゃないんだけれど
So you can't tell if you're feeling love...
この気持ちが恋かどうか
分からないとか
What are you, a girl?!
乙女か お前！
Sit
Sit!
Animation Number 64
正座！
Sit
Explain everything to me from the top, you useless brother.
どういうことなのか
最初から説明してちょうだい
このお兄ちゃん野郎
Well, um...
（暦）えっと その…
It's hard for me to put it in words, but...
あんまり具体的な話は
できないんだけど
Animation Number 64
Well, let's call this person H-san for now.
まあ とりあえず対象を
仮にＨさんとしよう
H-san?
（月火）Ｈさん
That's rather specific.
何だか具体的だね
She ended up in my class beginning this month.
今月の頭に
同じクラスになってから
Recollection
Before I knew it, I couldn't stop thinking about her.
どうも僕は気付けば
そのＨさんのことばかり
考えているみたいなんだ
H-san    H-san    H-san    H-san
And not just in my head, either.
頭の中だけのことじゃない
During class, my eyes drift from the blackboard over to her seat.
授業中とか ふと黒板から
視線を泳がせれば
Ｈさんの席を見てしまっている
And not just in school, either.
学校の中のことだけじゃない
On my way to and from school,
I find myself trying to look for her.
登下校中も 何となくＨさんを
探しちゃったりしてるわけだ
Yaharu Book Stores
National Library-Sized
Massive Book Store
Books
Cafe
Parking
When I go shopping at the bookstore, I find myself
本屋さんとかに買い物に行っても
狭い街なんだから
偶然 会えたりしないかなあ
Cooking Nutritious Food
How to Cook Meals for the Sick
Cooking Methods
and      Western Sweets
wondering if I might run into her since we live in a small town.
とか思っちゃったりな
And when I read a book that I've bought,
で その本屋さんで
買った本を読んでいても
I find myself thinking "Oh, H-san might like this line."
あっ この文章はＨさん好きそう
とか思うわけだ
And when I'm about to buy a dirty mag,
エッチな本とか買おうとしても
ああ こういう本を買っていたら
Ｈさんに嫌われる
I find myself thinking "Ah, H-san would
probably think I'm creepy if she saw this."
なんて思考が働いて
And so I put the book back on the shelf.
そっと本棚に
戻してしまったりもする
Onii-chan, please don't tell me everything in such vivid detail.
（月火）
お兄ちゃん
赤裸々に語りすぎないで
兄の個人情報を握りたくない
I don't want to know so much about your private life.
And I really don't want to hear about you hesitating whether or not to buy dirty magazines.
というかエッチな本を買うのに
ちゅうちょした兄の話なんて
聞きたくない
Wait, Onii-chan...
ていうか お兄ちゃん
What?
（暦）何だ？
（月火）それは恋でしょ
Isn't that love?
I don't know.
（暦）分かんねえぞ
I've never actually fallen in love with anyone before.
大体 僕 人を好きになったことって
ないんだよな
Say what?!
（月火）ないの〜？
（暦）皆無と言っていいね
Absolutely nil.
Sit
Animation Number 19
So I thought I'd ask about your experience for reference.
（暦）
参考までに お前の事例を
聞いてみようと思ったんだ
Your boyfriend—Rousokuzawa-kun, was it?
お前の彼氏 えっと…
蝋燭沢(ろうそくざわ)君だっけ？
（月火）うん よく覚えていたね
I'm surprised you remember.
（暦）名前だけな
Just the name.
When, and at what stage did you determine that you loved him?
お前は いつ どの段階で
そいつのことを好きだって
判断したんだ？
That's what I really want to know.
それを教えてほしいってのが
本当のところだ
Well, that's...
（月火）そんなのは まあ…
I just kind of knew.
何となくだよ
Just kind of knew?
何となく？
Right.
（月火）そう 曖昧 適当
Vaguely. Sort of.
（暦）そんなんでいいのか？
Just like that?
（月火）
そんなんでいいんだよ
そんなもんだよ
Just like that.
That's how it is.
Then let's leave aside the stage where it happened for now.
じゃあ どの段階でっていうのは
ひとまず置いておくとして
I'll ask you about why it happened instead.
どういう理由でっていうほうを
まずは聞かせてもらおうか
Rousokuzawa
Animation Number 104
Why did you fall in love with this Rousokuzawa-kun?
その蝋燭沢君を お前は
どうして好きになったんだ？
I just kind of did.
それも何となくだよ
But I really just kind of did.
でも本当に何となくなんだもん
Kind of
It just kind of kind of kind of happened.
何となくで 何となくで
何となくなんだもん
Kind of
I wondered if I loved him, and then I felt I did, and then I knew I did.
好きかなって思って
好きだなって感じて
好きだって分かる
That kind of thing.
そんな感じ！
Even vagueness has its limits.
ニュアンスにも程があるだろ
You can come up with any number of reasons why you love someone.
（月火）好きな理由にしたってさ
そりゃ いろいろ
こじつけることはできるよ
Like they're cool, or kind, or tall, or rich.
かっこいいとか 優しいとか
背が高いとか お金持ちとか
There are all sorts of reasons you can say,
そういう理由づけは
いろいろ可能だけどさ
but those are all lies.
けど そんなの全部ウソだもん
They're just excuses you tell yourself to rationally justify your emotions.
自分の気持ちを
理性で理解するための
“おためごかし”っていうのかな
Well, not so much excuses as tricks.
理由づけっていうよりは
こじつけだよ
It's like a ladder you climb, based on the conclusion that you love them.
好きだっていう結論ありきで
その結論に対して
ハシゴを掛けていくようなものだよ
A ladder?
（暦）ハシゴ…
Maybe not a ladder but a rocket?
ハシゴじゃなくてロケットかな
うん ロケットを作ってる感じ
It feels like you're creating a rocket.
When you feel like you want to be together forever, that's love.
ずっと 一緒にいたいと思ったら
それは もう恋なんだと思うよ
（暦）つうか なるほど
I get it now.
I, Araragi Koyomi-kun, 18 years of age, might have finally fallen in love!
そんな僕が
そんな僕こと
阿良々木(あららぎ) 暦君が今まさに
よわい18にして ついに
恋に落ちたかもしれないんだよ
Don't say "might have."
いや かもしれないなんて
言ってないで
もう決めつけちゃえばいいよ
Just say it out straight!
Say it out straight!
Animation Number 124
You know you did!
かもしれるよ！
Animation Number 125
You know you did!
I know I did...
かもしれるんだ
Animation Number 126
I know I did...
Onii-chan has fallen in love!
（月火）
お兄ちゃんは恋に落ちました
決定！
Definitely!
It's definite?!
（暦）決定したのか？
（月火）そう
Yeah!
Plans are never uncertain!
予定は未定じゃない！
Onii-chan, you love H-san. I've decided!
お兄ちゃんはＨさんのことが好き
私が決めた
I guess I can't say anything if you've decided.
（暦）
お前に決められちゃ しょうがない
I see.
そうだな
All right, it's all clear now!
よし 吹っ切れたぜ
Let me thank you.
礼を言わしてもらおう
ありがとう 月火ちゃん
Thanks
Animation Number 133
Thank you, Tsukihi-chan.
No, not at all.
いや いや いや いや
それほどのことは あるけどないよ
I didn't do anything but a bunch!
Well, everything I said aside, Onii-chan...
まあ いろいろ言っちゃったけどさ
お兄ちゃん
Falling in love is as natural as a dog barking.
人を好きになるなんて
犬がほえるくらい
当たり前のことなんだから
そんな思い悩むことなんか
ないんだよ
You shouldn't need to ponder over it so much.
I see. So it's natural.
（暦）そっか 当たり前か
Yep, totally normal.
（月火）うん 普通だよ
Animation Number 138
It's normal to be interested in a girl in your class.
（暦）
クラスに気になる女子が
いるのは普通
Normal.
Animation Number 139
Normal
（月火）普通！
It's normal to gaze at that girl instead of the blackboard during class.
Animation Number 140
（暦）
授業中 黒板よりも
その子の方を見ちゃうのも普通
Animation Number 141
Normal
Normal!
（月火）普通！
Animation Number 142
It's normal to look around hoping to run into that girl before or after school,
（暦）
登下校中 その子の姿を
探してしまうのも
偶然会えるかなあとか
考えてしまうのも
and to fantasize about her when buying magazines.
Animation Number 142
本を買うときに
いろいろと想像してしまうのも
Normal!
Animation Number 143
Normal
（月火）普通！
It's normal to want to grab her boobs—
Animation Number 144
（暦）
その子の胸をもみたいと思うのも
No.
No
Animation Number 145
（月火）違う
（暦）
えっ あれ 月火ちゃん
お前 一体 何を言ってるの？
Tsukihi-chan, what are you talking about?
（月火）
えっ あっ 私の側(がわ)ですか？
Huh? Wait, me?
Maybe you should sit, too.
お前も正座したほうが
いいんじゃない？
Oh... all right. I will.
あっ はい 分かりました
Sit
Animation Number 152
（暦）いや…
Sit
Well, H-san's breasts are incredibly attractive.
だからさ そのＨさんの胸部が
非常に魅力的なので
触りたい もみたいって
思うわけじゃないか
Isn't it natural to want to grope and fondle them?
Want to grope and fondle  Want to grope and fondle
That's what I'm asking.
今 そういう話をしているんだよ
Excuse me, Onii-chan.
ちょっとゴメン お兄ちゃん
Could you kindly stop using vulgar words like "grope" and "fondle"?
触るとか もむとか
露骨な言葉を使うのを
やめてもらっても
かまいませんか？
（暦）うん… そうか
All right...
Isn't it natural to want to touch them, then?
じゃあ タッチするしか
ないわけじゃないか
It went from vulgar to cute, but...
Animation Number 158
（月火）
露骨でなくなって
かわいくはなったけど
Well, in other words...
（暦）で つまりだ
Basically, before I knew it, I couldn't stop thinking about touching H-san's boobs.
要するに僕は 気が付けば
Ｈさんの胸にタッチしたい
ということばかり
考えているわけなんだが
That's love, right?
（暦）これは恋でいいんだな？
（月火）違う
No
No.
Animation Number 162
No
How come?
（暦）だが どうだ
You don't normally want to touch the boobs of someone you don't love, right?
好きでもない相手の胸に
タッチしたいとは思わないだろう
That's why I think this feeling must be love.
だから この気持ちは
恋に違いないと思うのだ
Onii-chan, it's perfectly natural for boys to want to touch girls' boobs.
（月火）お兄ちゃん
男の子が女の子のおっぱいに
タッチしたいと思うのは
自然な感情なんだから
You don't have to worry about that.
気にしなくたっていいんだよ
Geez...
まったく まったく まったく
Good grief...
What?
（暦）何だよ
（月火）試してみようと思って
I want to try something out.
Here, touch them.
（月火）ほれ 触ってみ？
（暦）うん
Wordlessly.
Expressionlessly.
Without thought or hesitation, he touched them.
Animation Number 169
Wordlessly.
Expressionlessly.
Without thought or hesitation, he touched them.
Wordlessly.
Expressionlessly.
Without thought or hesitation, he touched them.
Okay.
V
IV
III
II
I
えいっ
Not a touch, but a catch.
Animation Number 176
It hurts!
（月火）痛いわ〜！
（暦）うっ！
Red Scene
Animation Number "None"
That hurts, I said! Let go!
（月火）だから痛い 離せ 離せ
Let go! Let go!
（月火）離さんか！
（暦）うわ！
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?!
いや〜 もう！
お兄ちゃん
妹のおっぱい 触りすぎ！
What was the point of that in the first place?
Boobs Advisory
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?
ていうか
そもそも本当は
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?
どういうつもり
だったんだよ
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?
How did our conversation turn to you presenting your boobs to me?
どういう話の
流れになると思って
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?
お前は僕の前に胸を
突き出してきたんだよ
Geez, Onii-chan! Who grabs his little sister's boobs like that?
I guess you could call it an experiment or just a bad joke.
（月火）
まあ おふざけっていうか
お試しっていうか
My plan was to gross you out and have you say,
私の計画としては
お兄ちゃんが興味なさそうに
"No way, I don't care about your boobs."
“いや そんな胸には興味がない”
or something, and have you assert the validity of your theory.
とか言って自分の理論の正当性を
主張しようとするけれど
そこで私が
But then I'd answer, "Because they're your sister's, right?"
“妹の胸だからでしょ”って
ツッコミを入れるという—
for a fabulous verbal exchange rally!
見事なラリーをお返しする
シーンだったじゃない！
So what's the result?
（暦）
で 結局 どういうことになるんだ？
The result?
どういうことって？
What conclusion do you derive from this experiment of yours?
（暦）
そのお試しとやらで
どういう結論が導き出されるんだ？
Let's see...
（月火）えっとね
Onii-chan, you're sexually frustrated.
お兄ちゃん
欲求不満なんじゃない？
Say what?!
（暦）なんと！
（月火）ほら そういえばさっき
Well, you were saying just now,
"I didn't buy the dirty mag, I didn't buy
the dirty mag, I didn't buy the dirty mag!"
“エッチな本が買えない”
“エッチな本が買えない”って
言ってたじゃない
I didn't say it three times.
３回も言ってねえよ
That's why it had the opposite effect!
それが逆効果なんだよ
The complete opposite!
まるっきりの逆効果
Mistaking lust for love shows that you're caught in an inflationary spiral of sexual frustration.
性欲を恋と取り違えてしまった
お兄ちゃんは
そうやって
欲求不満のインフレスパイラルを
起こしちゃってるんだよ
なんてことだ！
インフレスパイラルだなんて
No way!
An inflationary spiral...
Such a 007-like phenomenon is occurring in my brain?
そんな「007」みたいな現象が
僕の脳内で起こっていると
お前は言うのか！
Yes.
（月火）
うん だから妹の胸にだって
見境なくタッチしちゃうんだよ
That's why you're able to touch your
sister's boobs without discrimination.
Touch them, huh?
（暦）タッチしちゃうのか
Like touching a touch panel?
タッチパネルみたいなその胸に
But a touch panel is completely flat!
（月火）
タッチパネルって平面じゃねえか！
I see.
（暦）
そうか 欲求不満か
Sexual frustration, huh?
Now that she mentions it, I can't really disagree.
しかし 言われてみれば
納得できないわけでもない
In fact, it makes perfect sense.
どころか
そのとおりだという気もする
Tsukihi:  "Good one, right?"
Koyomi:  "Not bad at all."
Animation Number 212
I see.
（暦）
なるほどな
そういうことだったのか
So that's what it was.
That was a close call, Onii-chan.
うん 危ないところだったね
お兄ちゃん
You almost believed you had fallen in love with a classmate you had no feelings for,
危うく好きでも何でもない
たかが胸が魅力的だというだけの
クラスメートに
恋をしていると
勘違いするところだったよ
simply because she has nice boobs.
I see, I see.
（暦）そうか そうか
これが本当の
This is really one of those "Don't get the wrong idea!" moments.
“勘違いしないでよね”って
ことだな
（月火）
この場合 Ｈさんにしてみれば
それ 切実なお願いだよね
In this case, H-san can legitimately say that to you.
Well, now that we've figured out the problem, we should work on a solution.
さて 結論が出たところで
次は対策を打たないとな
Right.
Animation Number 223
Bad things happen when you leave your sex drive unfulfilled.
欲求不満は放っておいたら
大変なことになる
Perhaps it's good fortune that I discovered the truth
with just a touch
Animation Number 223
Perhaps it's good fortune that I discovered the truth
with just a touch
I have to protect H-san from my evil hands.
Ｈさんを僕の魔手から守らなければ
Right.
Animation Number 224
As a temporary solution,
こそく療法として
気が向いたときに
お前とか火憐ちゃんとかの
おっぱいもんで スッキリしとくか
how about I grope Karen-chan's or your boobs to relieve myself whenever I feel like it?
There's no way we're letting you do that!
（月火）
そんな療法は
実行されてはならない！
Come on, you two are supposed to be the Fire Sisters, warriors of justice, right?
（暦）何だよ
お前らファイヤーシスターズって
正義の戦士なんだろ？
だったら僕のために
喜んで犠牲になれよ
You should be happy to make sacrifices for me.
I think real justice would be for you to be the sacrifice.
お兄ちゃんを犠牲にすることこそが
正義という気がするよ
I'd never let you grope me just
because you're bored and selfish.
そんな気ままな暇つぶし気分で
おっぱいを もまれてたまるか！
Then what am I supposed to do?
じゃあ どうするんだよ
I guess there's no avoiding it.
じゃ しかたないか
エッチな本を買えばいいよ
Just buy a dirty magazine.
That's the conclusion
Animation Number 234
You've been hesitant to buy any this past month
だから お兄ちゃんは勘違いで
Ｈさんの目を意識しちゃって
because you were worried about what H-san might think, right?
この１か月間 購入を
ちゅうちょしてきたんでしょ？
And knowing you,
ひょっとしたら
お兄ちゃんのことだし
I'll bet you got it in your head to purify yourself and throw out all your other dirty magazines, right?
心身の整理とか言って
これまでの秘蔵のお宝も
ヒモで縛って
捨てちゃったんじゃない？
H-How did you know that?!
（暦）なっ なぜそれを！
That only made your sexual frustration worse.
（月火）
それが欲求不満を
増進させていたんだよ
So you should just go out and buy some new ones, and that'll solve this whole problem!
だから エッチな本を
新規に購入することで
その辺りの問題を解決しちゃおう！
In that case, now's as good a time as any.
そうと決まれば善は急げだ
お兄ちゃん
The bookstore's open right now, so why don't you go buy some?
ちょうど本屋も
開くくらいの時間だし
今から買いに行けば？
I'm home!
（火憐）ただいま
Welcome back.
（暦）おかえり
What? Is it raining outside?
あっ 何？ 外 雨降ってるの？
I'm just about to head out.
僕 これから出かけるんだけど
No, it's not raining.
（火憐）いや 雨は降ってねえよ
It's bright and sunny, perfect for the first day of Golden Week.
ゴールデンウィークの初日に
ふさわしいピーカンさ
（暦）
は？ じゃあ なんで お前
そんなに ずぶぬれなんだよ
Then why are you completely soaked?
（火憐）いや これ 汗だよ
Well, this is sweat.
You're telling me all of that is sweat?
（暦）
それが全部 汗だと！ マジかよ！
Seriously?!
I don't usually jog, so I don't really know my limits.
いや あたし ジョギングって
そんなにしないから
加減が分かんなくってさ
I got the pace wrong.
ペース配分を間違っちまったようだ
（暦）へえ
（火憐）意外と長かったな
It took a surprisingly long time.
42.195 kilometers.
42,195キロ
You ran a full marathon?!
お前 フルマラソンを
走ってきたのか！
It was to celebrate the beginning of Golden Week,
and an Olympic Torch Bearer is the image I get from it.
（火憐）だってほら
今日はゴールデンウィーク
開始祝いのジョギングで
イメージは
聖火ランナーだったから
（暦）
聖火ランナーは
42,195キロも走らねえよ！
Olympic Torch Bearers don't run 42.195 kilometers!
Man, I'm exhausted.
（火憐）はあ 疲れた
And thirsty. I need water!
つうか 喉 渇いた 水 水！
ぷはっ！
はあ〜ん さ〜て
シャワーでも浴びてくっかな
Now then...
I guess I'll take a shower.
Hey, Karen-chan.
（暦）なあ 火憐ちゃん
What, Nii-chan?
何だよ 兄ちゃん
There's something I want to ask.
ちょっと教えてほしいことが
あるんだけど
So you finally want to walk the path of Karate?
（火憐）
何だ ついに 兄ちゃんも
空手道を歩みたくなったのか？
No, I don't want to ask about moves.
（暦）
いや 教えてほしいことというのは
奥義とかじゃない
How do you decide whether or not you've fallen in love, or that you love somebody?
お前さ
自分が恋をしているかどうか
相手のことを
好きかどうかっていうのを
どんなふうに判断する？
What, relationship advice?
（火憐）はあ 何だ 恋愛相談かよ
If you look at someone and think that you want to have their kid,
顔 見て コイツのガキを
産みてえなって思ったら
isn't that what love is?
それが好きってこと
なんじゃねえの？
Animation Number 278
Taxi
おおっと！ えっ？
Oh.
（翼(つばさ)）あっ ヤッホ〜 阿良々木君
Hey, Araragi-kun!
Yay!
イエ〜イ 元気してる？
You doing fine?
Hey.
ヤッホ イエイ… 元気してる…
Yay, I'm doing fine...
Failure
Animation Number 297
う… えっと
Um...
Animation Number 300
Hey, Araragi-kun—
（翼）
えっとね 阿良々木君！
（暦）えい！
（翼）キャ〜！
Red Scene
Animation Number "None"
You're in high school and you're still flipping skirts?
（翼）
高校生にもなって
スカートめくりって
何を考えているの 阿良々木君
What are you thinking, Araragi-kun?
Um, Hanekawa...
あのね 羽川(はねかわ)
I know.
（翼）分かってるよ
Here.
ほら
You're kind, Araragi-kun.
優しいね 阿良々木君
You're a kind and good person.
（翼）優しくて いい人だね
That's what I like about you.
私はね 阿良々木君の
そういうところが好きだよ
How about we walk for a bit?
歩こっか 少し
I
Araragi-kun, you have sisters, don't you?
阿良々木君って 確か
妹がいるんだったよね
Yeah.
Two sisters that I really don't need.
いなくてもいいような妹が２人
Now that's not very nice.
いなくてもいいって
We're still family, so it's not like we're on bad terms.
（暦）
まあ いっても家族だからさ
険悪ってことはない
But it's true that they cause me all sorts of trouble.
だけど いろいろ
迷惑をかけられているのも本当だ
Though I do cause them a little trouble myself.
とはいえ 僕のほうからも
ちょっとくらいは
迷惑をかけたこともあるだろうし
（翼）お互いさまってとこ？
So it evens things out?
Isn't that nice? Just how a family should be.
いいじゃん それ家族っぽくて
Family?
（暦）家族？
（翼）うん ファミリー
That's right. Family.
私が 一人っ子だっていうのは
言ったっけ？
Did I tell you I'm an only child?
I don't think you did.
（暦）いや 聞いてないと思う
You see, Araragi-kun...
だからさ 阿良々木君
私には家族っていないんだよね
I have no family.
（暦）うん？ おいおい 羽川
Hang on, Hanekawa.
Just because you don't have siblings, it doesn't mean you have no family.
兄弟がいないだけで
家族がいないは言い過ぎだろ
There's your dad, your mom, your grandpa, your grandma...
お父さんとか お母さんとか
おじいちゃんとか
おばあちゃんとか
No.
いない　お父さんもお母さんも
誰もいないよ
I don't have a father or mother, or anybody.
I don't.
私には
Basically, my mother's husband's second wife is my mother now,
（翼）
つまりね お母さんの結婚相手の
再婚相手が今の母親で
and her new husband is my father now.
その再婚相手が
今の父親ってことになるね
In other words, your parents aren't your actual parents?
（暦）
要するに 今の両親は
本当の両親じゃないってことか
Yes.
（翼）
そう 今 一緒に暮らしてる
お父さんとお母さん
My current mother and father aren't at all related by blood to me.
私と全く
血が つながってないんだよ
-
1 B
We're complete strangers.
いうなら赤の他人なの
-
1 B
ONE COIN
ウフフ
Red is the color of strangers,
but I'm also unrelated by blood.
血がつながってないのに
赤の他人って
If a vampire heard that, he'd laugh his head off.
吸血鬼が聞いたら
笑いそうな話だよね
He wouldn't.
（暦）笑えねえよ
I used to believe that being family
didn't require you to be blood-related.
血がつながってなくても
家族になれるって
私も昔は そう思ってたんだけどね
I tried my best to get along with them.
頑張って仲良くしようとか
思ってたんだけどね
But I couldn't change a thing.
ままならないもんだよ 本当に
I couldn't change a thing, and it sucks.
ままならないし つまらないよ
Who did that to your face?
その顔 誰にやられた？
Why would you ask that?
（翼）
どうしてそんなことを
聞くのかな？
Why would you want to know, Araragi-kun?
どうして 阿良々木君が
そんなことを？
Because...
（暦）それは
Because I'm your friend... I think.
それは 多分 僕が
お前の友達だからだろ
（翼）友達…
My friend?
Aren't friends supposed to hear you out in these situations?
（暦）
友達なら
話を聞くもんじゃねえのか
こういう場合…
I'm not too sure, though.
よく分かんないけど
（翼）
う〜ん そっか そうだね
そうかも
I see.
Yes, you're probably right.
Will you promise not to tell anyone?
誰にも言わないって
約束してくれる？
Yeah, I...
うん そりゃ
Don't tell anyone. I mean anyone.
（翼）
誰にもだよ 本当に誰にも
妹さんたちにも
Not your sisters.
Not your family.
家族にも秘密
I promise.
（暦）約束… する
My father hit me this morning.
今朝 お父さんに殴られたの
（暦）殴られたって それは…
Hit?
That's—
Just think about it, Araragi-kun.
ほら だって考えてみてよ
阿良々木君
Imagine you were about 40,
もしも阿良々木君が
40歳くらいでさ
and this 17-year-old kid you don't even know spoke to you like she knew it all.
見も知らぬ17歳の子供から
知ったような口を利かれたとして
It's only natural that you'd get mad or
that something would snap inside you.
ちょっと腹が立っちゃっても
カチンときちゃっても
それは しかたがないと思わない？
Why is she belittling herself like that?
（暦）
何だその 自虐的な言い方は
She's sticking up for a parent who's not even her real parent...
親ではない親を
娘を殴るような親を
A parent who hit her.
かばおうとしている
As her friend...
そんな羽川が 僕は友人として
As her friend
Animation Number 383
That sickened me.
素直に気持ち悪かった
Violence is only natural?
（暦）
暴力が しかたないなんて
何 言ってんだよ
What are you talking about?
Do you really think that?
お前がそんな言葉を
吐いちまっていいのか！
That makes you even worse—
それはお前が
最も許せないことじゃ…
What's wrong?
いいじゃない
（翼）１回くらい
（暦）あっ
It's just once.
You promised, right, Araragi-kun?
（翼）約束したよね 阿良々木君
約束したよね 阿良々木君
You promised that you wouldn't tell anyone, right?
誰にも言わないって
約束してくれたよね
B-But...
（暦）
で… でも そんな約束なんて
But I can't...
I can't keep that promise.
約束なんて守れるはずが…
お願い 阿良々木君！
I beg you, Araragi-kun!
Please don't tell anyone.
このことは
誰にも言わないでください
Hanekawa...
（暦）羽川…
だけど 僕は
But I...
Please don't tell anyone.
（翼）
このことは
誰にも言わないでください
I'll do anything if you keep quiet.
黙っていてくれたら
私 何でもするから
Really?!
（暦）
えっ マジで！ 羽川が
何でもしてくれるの？
You'll do anything?
Hell yeah!
やった〜！
A-Araragi-kun?
（翼）あ… 阿良々木君？
What now?
（暦）うわ どうしよう！
（翼）あっ…
What should I make her do?
（暦）
何してもらおう？
What would be best to make her do?
何をしてもらうのが
ベストなんだろう
No!
（暦）いや！
（翼）あっ…
Wait, slow down!
待て 待て 慌てるな 僕！
Don't get ahead of yourself here.
浮足立つな
こういうときこそ クールにだ
Gotta stay cool at times like this.
Take this seriously!
おごそかにいけ〜！
You gotta make the most of this unprecedented opportunity!
この未曽有のチャンスを
最大限に生かすんだ！
H-Huh?
あっ あれ
そんなリアクションなの？
Th-That's your reaction?
ここって そういうシーンなの？
Is that how this scene's supposed to go?
阿良々木君が私の真摯(しんし)さに
心を打たれて
Aren't you meant to be touched by my sincerity and reluctantly promise to keep my secret?
しぶしぶながらも沈黙を
約束してくれるシーンじゃないの？
（暦）
真摯さ？ 何だ そりゃ 知らん！
Sincerity?
What's that? Never heard of it!
"Ms. Tsubasa will listen to anything
Araragi-kun begs for ☆"
Animation Number 412
"Ms. Tsubasa will listen to anything
Araragi-kun begs for ☆"
Anything, huh?
何でもか〜
Who the hell's Ms. Tsubasa?
Animation Number 413
That makes this difficult though...
しかし そう言われてしまうと
迷っちゃうなあ
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
Animation Number 414
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
I was exploring the situation of Hanekawa
playing a female teacher and
accidentally let it slip
Damn it!
クソ！ 自分の優柔不断さが
悩ましいぜ〜
My indecisiveness is a serious problem!
This calls for a quick decision!
こういうときに
ビシッと決断できてこそ
Decisiveness would make me a man among men.
男の中の男だろうに
No, that would make you the worst of men.
（翼）いや 最低の男だと思う
Hey, Araragi-kun.
ねえ 阿良々木君
さっきまで私たちが話してた—
Do you still remember that serious and heavy stuff we were just talking about?
シリアスで重い話の内容
覚えてる？
Not at all.
（暦）覚えていない！
（翼）覚えてないんだ…
So you don't.
And who's Araragi?
（暦）阿良々木とは誰だ？
You even forgot your own name...
（翼）
自分の名前も忘れちゃったんだ…
So you'd do anything?
（暦）“何でもする”か〜
But seriously, what should I make you do?
しかし本当に 果たして
何をさせてばいいんだ？
The multitude of choices is exactly what makes the decision difficult!
選択肢が多すぎるからこそ
これは迷う！
いや むしろ これは小論文だ！
No, this is a thesis!
My ability to put an argument together is being put to the test!
僕には 今 構成力が
要求されている！
Wait!
待てよ　そういえば
Come to think of it, Hanekawa, you never said how many wishes you'd grant me.
羽川は かなえる願いの数を
限定していない
Depending on how you interpret what you said, it could
mean that you'll grant me an unlimited number of wishes!
つまり さっきの言葉
取りようによれば 僕の言うことを
無限に聞いてくれるという
意味じゃないのか！
（翼）１つです！
Just one!
I'll listen to one thing you say.
何でも１つだけ
言うことを聞くから
Damn, she clarified it.
クッ 釈明させてしまったぜ
ホント もう頭痛がしてきたよ
You're starting to give me a headache.
For now, let's go somewhere quieter.
（暦）
とりあえず
人けのない場所に行こうか 羽川
Fine, fine, I'll come.
はい はい 分かりました
どうせ 行くとこなんてないしね
It's not like I need to be anywhere after all.
I brought Hanekawa into the nearby bushes.
（暦）
羽川を近くの茂みに連れ込んだ
I brought Hanekawa into the nearby bushes.
What is it, Araragi-kun?
何よ 阿良々木君
You're making a pretty big deal out of this...
随分と もったいぶるじゃない
それとも
何も思いつかないのかな？
Or are you not able to come up with anything?
それとも それとも
Or did you just want to check out my entire body like you're doing now?
そうやって私の全身を
なめるように見ることが
阿良々木君のしたいことなの？
視姦(しかん)ってやつ？
Eye-rape, basically?
Hanekawa.
（暦）羽川
（翼）何？
What?
Checking out your body isn't what I want to do.
（暦）
全身をなめるように見ることが
僕のしたいことではない
僕は
I...
（暦）
僕は お前のそのガーゼの下の
殴られた傷を
I want to lick the wound...
...under that gauze.
なめ回したいのだ！
Animation Number 456
There are still some after-effects
remaining from when I was a vampire.
（暦）
吸血鬼だったころの後遺症が
残っている僕の血や唾液は
One of those is the ability of my blood and saliva to heal wounds.
ケガの治療をすることが可能なのだ
I should note that I'm a coward and don't actually have the courage to lick Hanekawa's face,
一応 注釈をしておくと
実際には羽川の顔面を
なめ回す度胸のない—
チキン僕が取ったのは
so I used the safety pin on her bag to prick my finger and apply some of my blood to Hanekawa's wound.
カバンに付いていた安全ピンで
指先を刺して
そこから出た血を
羽川の患部に塗るという—
極めて健全な行為だったりする
It was the safest way to go about it.
Thank you.
（翼）ありがとう
You should put your gauze back on.
（暦）
一応 ガーゼ 貼り直しとけよ
いきなりケガが治ってたら
おかしいだろ
They might think something's off if they see no wound.
（翼）親が不審に思う？
You think my parents would be suspicious?
They wouldn't.
（翼）思わないよ
（暦）ん…
They aren't like that.
（翼）そういう人たちじゃないから
They wouldn't notice even if I shaved all my hair off.
私が髪をバッサリ切っても
あの人たちは
気付かないんじゃないかな
多分 あの人たちは…
In fact, they probably...
私の顔も覚えてない
...don't even remember my face.
Nii-chan?
（火憐）
おう 兄ちゃん 何だ 早かったな
That was fast.
Hey, don't just ignore me, Nii-chan!
何だよ 無視するなよ 兄ちゃん
You should at least greet your
adorable sister when you're back.
かわいい妹に
ただいまくらい言えよ
買い物は済んだのか？
Did you finish your shopping?
（暦）買い物？
Shopping?
いや 買い物は…
Oh...
I...
（暦）
していない
...wasn't shopping.
Instead of relieving my frustration, I only managed to make it worse.
欲求不満の解消どころか
モヤモヤとした気持ちは
増すばかりだ
My feelings, my thoughts, everything...
思う思いは重く
weighed down upon me.
募るばかり
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Here's your preview hallucination.
We're Going to Rock New Year's!
We!
Are the Fire Sisters!
（旧キスショット）
予告幻聴じゃ
Do you know about a little animal called water bear?
クマムシという
生き物がおってのう
We gotta hurry!
We might not make it to the New Year's broadcast!
It can enter a period of dehydrated sleep unlike hibernation, and has been called immortal.
冬眠ならぬ乾眠をする性質があって
不死身とさえ言われるのじゃ
Hey my sisters! Use this!
Thanks, brother!
Rumbling
They call it cryptobiosis, you see.
クリプトビオシスというやつじゃな
Though it can tolerate extremely adverse conditions, it is weak to being squashed underfoot.
めちゃくちゃ過酷な環境にも
耐えられる生物なのじゃが
This way!
Oh! Hanekawa-san!
潰したら死ぬという弱点を持つ
Spin!
It's actually this way!
Thanks!
Are you a vampire or something?
うぬは吸血鬼か？
Next time. Tsubasa Family, Part 2.
次回「つばさファミリー 其ノ貮(そのに)」
Next Time
Tsubasa Family Part 2
生物 みな家族
All living beings are a family.
She transformed!
We didn't make it on time.